Guide to the League of Women Voters of Montana records 1921-1989
Montana Historical Society Research Center
League of Women Voters of Montana records
1921-1989
Montana Historical Society Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 180
League of Women Voters of Montana
8 linear feet of shelf space.
The League of Women Voters is a non-partisan political organization. Records (1921-1989) of the Montana branch include general correspondence arranged by president; financial records; minutes; organizational materials; reports to the national office; subject files; miscellany; and clippings. There are also records for local branches of the League around the state.
Historical Note:
The League of Women Voters (LWV), a national membership organization works on the national, state, and community levels of government to promote political responsibility through informed and active participation of citizens in their government. The League takes action in support of or in opposition to selected governmental issues, but it does not support or oppose candidates nor support or oppose political parties. Nonpartisanship is an established policy. A citizen eighteen or older joins at the local level and works through the local League on the three levels beginning with community government. In 1974 membership was opened to men. On February 14, 1920, Carrie Chapman Catt, president of the National American Woman Suffrage Association, at its six-months-premature victory celebration of the upcoming ratification of the 19th Amendment at convention in Chicago, spearheaded the founding of the LWV as a way to educate newly franchised voters.
Montana women had been granted the vote in 1914 and were eager to join the League. The first Montana League organization meeting was held in Great Falls on April 26, 1920, where plans were made to establish bylaws for the regional convention. This convention was held in Butte on May 25, 1921, and Mrs. A.F. Rice of Butte was elected president. The first convention established the objectives and policies of the Montana League of Women Voters to work toward efficient government, the good of public welfare in government, and international cooperation to prevent war. The League declared that it would not align itself with any political party but that it could endorse measures and policies. The League also declared that it would urge every woman to become a registered voter. Early Montana League members included Jeannette Rankin, Maggie Smith Hathaway, Frieda Fligelman, Belle Fligelman Winestine, and Dr. Mary B. Atwater.
The Montana League was a loosely structured organization in the state during the early 1920s and 1930s with the members meeting in Helena during the legislative sessions. The League was inactive during the World War II years. After 1946 the League of Women Voters of the United States (LWVUS) provided funds from the Carrie Chapman Catt Trust to employ an organizing secretary who would work to organize local and state Leagues in six western states. Irene Sweeney, national organizer, came to Montana to organize local Leagues in six selected communities. By 1952 local Leagues were established in Billings, Butte, Great Falls, Havre, Helena, and Missoula. The next step was to bring these local Leagues into a state organization. In 1953 a meeting of 29 delegates was held in Helena, and Laura Nicholson, a Helena member, was elected to begin the organizational work. The State Organization Committee coordinated a program of study of state government, with each local League investigating some phase of government. In April 1955 the first state convention was held in Butte. Catherine Jones of Missoula was elected first state president, an agenda was adopted, a budget prepared, and the LWVMT has continued under this format ever since. The LWVMT brings together the local Montana Leagues and works at the state government level.
In 1988 there were eight local Leagues; Billings, Bozeman, Flathead County (Kalispell, Whitefish), Great Falls, Liberty County (Chester), Helena, Missoula, and Ravalli County (Hamilton). Interested citizens who live outside established local Leagues may join as members-at-large (MALS) and they become the responsibility of the state board. Several local Leagues which have dissolved continue their members in MAL status including Butte, Miles City, and Havre. LWVMT is financed by local Leagues' per-member payments set by the state Board of Directors. Officers and Board members are elected at its biennial convention. In 1987 for the first time LWVMT hired a paid lobbyist, funded by contributions from members.
The LWVUS works at the national level of government, supporting and opposing issues on which a grass roots position has been taken. There are Leagues in all fifty states, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, and Hong Kong. Headquarters for the national elected officers and Board of Directors is in Washington, D.C. Officers and Board members receive no salary. The LWVUS is financed by membership dues and contributions from members and interested public citizens. The League of Women Voters Education Fund (LWVEF) is a separate educational arm, responsible for raising funds to enable the LWVUS to carry on its program of work in the field of political activity. LWVEF has a paid professional staff, researches the critical political, social, and economic issues, and prepares educational materials for wide distribution. The League works on governmental issues chosen by the membership. Six months before the biennial national convention, local Leagues begin a discussion of issues and send in recommendations for the national program. The national Board considers these issues and sends a "Proposed Program" to Leagues for a second round of discussion. Final decisions are made by majority vote of delegates in convention. State and local programs are selected by the same general democratic procedure as in the national program. The program is divided into two parts: current agenda, issues selected for concentrated study and concerted action (such as environmental quality or welfare reform); and continuing responsibilities, positions on issues to which the League has given sustained attention and on which it may continue to take action (such as land use or voting rights). Position statements formed through the process of discussion and consensus at the local unit eetings are summarized, printed, and made available to members who may use them to lobby at the local government level. Position statements adopted by the LWVMT are summarized and published in the group's handbook. Topics of concern to the LWVMT in the past have included Montana institutions, executive reorganization, and constitutional revision. LWVMT members and officers may serve as volunteer lobbyists during the legislative sessions. All local and state Leagues are active in Voters Service, publish factual information on issues, conduct candidates meetings, register voters, hold candidates debates, monitor polling places, and work to get out the vote.
The records of the League of Women Voters of Montana include general correspondence (1953-1989) arranged by president; financial records (1955-1981); minutes (1953-1989) of Board, Council, and Convention meetings; organizational materials (1921-1989) including standards for organizations, Convention programs, lists of officers, etc.; reports (1956-1987) to National League and of the Board; speeches (1981); subject files (1954-1988) including agenda items and other topics arranged alphabetically; miscellany (1956-1976); and clippings (1952-1986).
Records of the local Leagues are arranged in additional subgroups, arranged alphabetically (Billings, Bozeman, Butte, Flathead County, Great Falls, Havre, Helena, Liberty County, Missoula, Ravalli County, and South Lincoln County). Materials in the local League subgroups include general correspondence, financial records, minutes, organizational materials, reports, miscellany (including agenda items, studies, etc.), and clippings.
by subgroup and series
Acquisition information available upon request
Printed materials, artifacts, and photographs have been separated to the Library, Museum, and Photo Archives respectively.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Elections--Montana.
Energy development--Montana.
Environmental policy--Montana.
Government reorganization--Montana.
Land use--Montana.
Local government--Montana.
Voter registration--Montana.
Water--Pollution--Montana.
Water-supply--Montana.
Women in politics--Montana.
Women--Societies and clubs--Montana.
Billings (Mont.)--Politics and government
Bozeman (Mont.)--Politics and government
Butte (Mont.)--Politics and government
Flathead County (Mont.)--Politics and government
Great Falls (Mont.)--Politics and government
Havre (Mont.)--Politics and government
Helena (Mont.)--Politics and government
Kalispell (Mont.)--Politics and government
Libby (Mont.)--Politics and government
Liberty County (Mont.)--Politics and government
Lincoln County (Mont.)--Politics and government
Missoula (Mont.)--Politics and government
Montana--Politics and government
Ravalli County (Mont.)--Politics and government
Montana
Government and Politics
Women
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- League of Women Voters of Montana
  - General Correspondence
    - State Organization Committee Chairperson's file: Laura Nicholson, Helena, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - President's file: Catherine Jones, Missoula (includes president's reports), 1955-1959 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - President's file: Marjorie Lou Foster, Missoula (includes president's reports), 1959 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - President's file: Marjorie Lou Foster, Missoula, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - President's file: Virginia Griffing, Great Falls (includes president's bulletins), 1963-1965 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - President's file: Virginia Griffing, Great Falls, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - President's file: Dorothy Eck, Bozeman, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - President's file: Dorothy Eck, Bozeman, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - President's file: Jean Anderson, Billings, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - President's file: Jean Anderson, Billings, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - President's file: Gladys Elison, Missoula, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - President's file: Mary Hempleman, Great Falls, 1974 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - President's file: Mary Hempleman, Great Falls, 1975 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - President's file: Mary Hempleman, Great Falls, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - President's file: Priscella McLean, Ravalli, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - President's file: Ardelle Hurlburt, Havre, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - President's file: Margaret Davis, Helena, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - President's file: Diane Young, Great Falls, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - President's file: Jenny R. Redfern, Billings, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
    - President's file: Chris Ebling, Great Falls, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - President's file: Joy Bruck, Helena, 1988 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 3 / 7-9)
  - Financial Records
    - Budgets; financial reports; treasurer's reports, 1955-1989 (Box-folder 3 / 10-13)
    - Taxes, 1968-1981 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Minutes
    - State Organization Committee Meetings; State Board meetings, 1953-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
    - State Board meetings, 1960-1989 (Box-folder 4 / 3-7)
    - State Convention and State Council meetings, 1955-1984 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Organization
    - Adopted state program, 1975-1987 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
    - "Basic Documents" of organization (photocopies from National League), 1921-1937 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
    - Bylaws, 1955-1981 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
    - Incorporation and trade names, 1952-1985 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
    - Lists of state officers, board members, local League officers, and committee chairs, 1956-1987 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
    - Standards for provisional, state, local Leagues and members-at-large; nonpartison policy; memberships for men citizens; guidelines for local Leagues, committee chairs, lobbyist, Board members, finance drives, etc., 1961-1986 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
    - State Convention programs, 1955-1963, 1965-1989 (Box-folder 5 / 5-6)
    - State Council programs, 1958-1984 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Photographs
    - List of photographs separated to Photo Archives (Box-folder 5 / 8)
  - Printed Material
    - The Montana Voter, (statewide newsletter, scattered issues), Mar. 1974- Mar. 1990 (Box-folder 5 / 9)
    - List of printed material separated to the Library (Box-folder 5 / 10)
  - Reports
    - State annual reports to National League, 1956-1979, 1987 (Box-folder 6 / 1-3)
    - State Board report, 1961-1972, 1975-1983 (Box-folder 6 / 4-7)
  - Speeches
    - re the League by Laura Nicholson, 1981 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
  - Subject Files
    - Agenda item: Montana Constitution (scattered), 1954-1972 (Box-folder 7 / 1-2)
    - Agenda item: Montana Constitution with emphasis on fiscal relationship between local and state gorvernment, 1956 (Box-folder 7 / 3)
    - Agenda item: constitutional revision study, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 7 / 4)
    - Agenda item: Constitutional Convention (includes League members as delegates to Convention), 1972 (Box-folder 7 / 5)
    - Agenda item: local government review and workshop, 1963-1974 (Box-folder 7 / 6)
    - Agenda item: national government re examining the presidency, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 7 / 7)
    - Agenda item: national government re "Freedom Agenda Project" (re individual liberties), 1955-1965 (Box-folder 7 / 8)
    - Agenda item: national government re opposition to a constitutional limitation on tax rates, 1962 (Box-folder 7 / 9)
    - Agenda item: state government re campaign finances and practices, 1975 (Box-folder 7 / 10)
    - Agenda item: state government re executive reorganization, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 7 / 11)
    - Agenda item: state government re finance and budget processes, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 8 / 1)
    - Agenda item: state government re unicameral legislature, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 8 / 2)
    - Agenda item: human resources re welfare (includes child care), 1970-1988 (Box-folder 8 / 3)
    - Agenda item: Montana institutions (Montana State Hospital; mental health), 1958-1977 (Box-folder 8 / 4)
    - Agenda item: Montana institutions (Boulder River School and Hospital; Montana Children's Home at Twin Bridges; Eastmont Training Center), 1967-1975 (Box-folder 8 / 5)
    - Agenda item: Montana institutions (State Prison; ciminal justice system; includes Gay Ashton's correspondence), 1967-1977 (Box-folder 8 / 6-8)
    - Agenda item: international relations re foreign trade, 1962-1980 (Box-folder 8 / 9)
    - Agenda item: international relations re Panama Canal, 1977 (Box-folder 9 / 1)
    - Agenda item: international relations re United Nations, 1961-1976 (Box-folder 9 / 2)
    - Agenda item: natural resources re energy (includes Colstrip 3 and 4; coal tax), 1972-1988 (Box-folder 9 / 3-4)
    - Agenda item: natural resources re environmental quality (air pollution; solid waste management; water pollution; strip mining; includes Harriet Marble's correspondence), 1967-1987 (Box-folder 9 / 5-6)
    - Agenda item: natural resources re land use, 1973-1978 (Box-folder 9 / 7)
    - Agenda item: natural resources re land and water use seminars, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 9 / 8)
    - Agenda item: natural resources re water quality of Missoula and Yellowstone Basins, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 9 / 9)
    - Agenda item: natural resources re water studies (includes water marketing), 1957-1985 (Box-folder 10 / 1-2)
    - Agenda item: public school finance, 1966-1982 (Box-folder 10 / 3)
    - "Canon 35" review (cameras in courtroom), 1977-1980 (Box-folder 10 / 4)
    - Capital City Status of Women Committee, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 10 / 5)
    - Columbia River Basin Fask Force, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 10 / 6-7)
    - Courts/Public Education Task Force, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 10 / 8)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (includes Belle Winestine Recognition Day; National ERA research project with editing done by Margaret S. Davis), 1973-1988 (Box-folder 10 / 9)
    - Kootenai River Dam project, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 10 / 10)
    - "Know Your State" booklet, 1965-1987 (Box-folder 10 / 11)
    - League of Women Voters of Montana vs Montana High School Association (re discrimination in high school athletics), 1985-1987 (Box-folder 10 / 12)
    - Legislative Action (re League Day at legislature; position statements; reports on legislative interviews; testimony prepared for legislature; fact sheets; correspondence of Daphne Bugbee), 1961-1989 (Box-folder 11 / 1-5)
    - Members-At-Large/Organization Committee (re MALS at Miles City, Alberton, Lewistown, etc.), 1952-1981 (Box-folder 11 / 6-7)
    - Montana Investment Study project, 1981 (Box-folder 11 / 8)
    - The Montana Jefferson Meetings (re bicentennial of U.S. Constitution), 1986-1987 (Box-folder 11 / 9)
    - Nuclear Energy Education Project (includes energy puppet shows), 1979-1982 (Box-folder 11 / 10)
    - Jeannette Rankin statue, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 11 / 11)
    - Tri-State Humanities Project (re coal and water development), 1974 (Box-folder 11 / 12)
    - Voters service (candidates debates), 1984-1988 (Box-folder 11 / 13)
    - Voters service (candidates questionnaires, etc.), 1956-1978 (Box-folder 12 / 1-2)
    - Workshops (re finance, leadership training, litigation, publication, practical politics, membership-management), 1963-1987 (Box-folder 12 / 3)
  - Miscellany
    - Financing the League questionnaires (from Missoula, Helena, Billings Locals; finance drive information), 1975 (Box-folder 12 / 4)
    - List of artifacts separated to the Museum (Box-folder 12 / 5)
    - National program planning recommendations from local leagues, 1961-1976 (Box-folder 12 / 6-7)
    - Proclamation for League of Women Voters Week in Montana; list of Montanans attending national convention; map of Leagues; letterhead, 1956, 1960, n.d. (Box-folder 12 / 8)
  - Clippings
    - League of Women Voters of Montana, 1952-1986 (Box-folder 12 / 9-10)
- League of Women Voters of Billings
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (scattered), 1957-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 13 / 1-2)
  - Financial Records
    - Budgets, financial reports, 1959-1977 (Box-folder 13 / 3)
  - Minutes
    - General League meetings; Board meetings, 1952-1974, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 13 / 4-8)
  - Organization
    - Membership and officer lists; bylaws, 1956-1980 (Box-folder 13 / 9)
  - Printed Material
    - The Billings Voter, newsletter of the Billings League, Apr. 1973 (Box-folder 13 / 10)
    - List of printed materials separated to the Library (Box-folder 13 / 11)
  - Reports
    - Annual reports (includes recommendations to National League), 1953-1966 (Box-folder 13 / 12)
    - Annual reports (includes recommendations to National League), 1967-1980 (Box-folder 14 / 1)
  - Miscellany
    - Agendas; "concensus" forms re local League's position on various issues; studies (re United Nations' Day, nursing homes, local government, state government, schools, water, custodial institutions, delinquency, voters service, judicial system, etc.), 1956-1982 (Box-folder 14 / 2-3)
    - Programs; histories of Billings League; informational booklets, 1960-1987 (Box-folder 14 / 4)
  - Clippings
    - re Billings League, 1958-1973 (Box-folder 14 / 5)
- League of Women Voters of Bozeman
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1958-1978, n.d. (Box-folder 14 / 6)
  - Financial Records
    - Budgets, finance drive report, 1956, 1978-1980,n.d. (Box-folder 14 / 7)
  - Minutes
    - General League meetings; Board meetings, 1955-1969, 1973-1983 (Box-folder 14 / 8-10)
  - Organization
    - Membership and officer lists; bylaws; application for Provisional League status, 1956-1972 (Box-folder 14 / 11)
  - Printed Material
    - List of printed materials separated to Library (Box-folder 14 / 12)
  - Reports
    - Annual reports (includes recommendations to National League), 1958-1969, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 15 / 1-2)
  - Miscellany
    - Agendas; "concensus" forms of local League's position on various issues; studies (re Gallatin County rest home, fair housing, city-county government, institutions, energy conservation grant, voters service, etc.), 1959-1987 (Box-folder 15 / 3)
    - Brochures; programs, 1966, 1972,n.d. (Box-folder 15 / 4)
  - Clippings
    - re Bozeman League, 1983,n.d. (Box-folder 15 / 5)
- League of Women Voters of Butte
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (scattered), 1952-1979 (Box-folder 15 / 6-7)
  - Financial Records
    - Budgets; financial reports, 1952-1979 (Box-folder 15 / 8)
  - Minutes
    - General League meetings; Board meetings (includes organizational meeting for League of Women Voters of Montana, 1951), 1951-1954 (Box-folder 15 / 9)
    - General League meetings; Board meetings, 1955-1964, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 15 / 10-12)
  - Organization
    - Membership and officer lists; bylaws; applications for Provisional and local League status, 1951-1964, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 15 / 13)
  - Printed Material
    - List of printed materials separated to Library (Box-folder 15 / 14)
  - Reports
    - Annual reports (includes recommendations to National League), 1955, 1958-1976 (Box-folder 15 / 15)
  - Subject Files
    - Membership drives; financial drives, 1955-1975 (Box-folder 16 / 1)
  - Miscellany
    - Agendas; "concensus" forms re local League's position on various issues; studies (re local governement, schools, voters service, etc.), 1955-1982 (Box-folder 16 / 2)
    - Programs; brochures, 1955-1975 (Box-folder 16 / 3)
    - Spot announcements for radio; television puppet shows; radio scripts from candidate forums, 1956-1960, n.d. (Box-folder 16 / 4)
  - Clippings
    - re Butte League, 1955-1963, 1975,n.d. (Box-folder 16 / 5)
- League of Women Voters of Flathead County
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1954-1959, 1974-1987 (Box-folder 16 / 6)
  - Financial Records
    - Budgets; financial reports, 1956-1981 (Box-folder 16 / 7)
  - Minutes
    - General League meetings; Board meetings, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 16 / 8)
    - General League meetings; Board meetings, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 16 / 9)
  - Organization
    - Membership and officer lists; bylaws; application for local League status, 1957-1987 (Box-folder 16 / 10)
  - Printed Material and Maps
    - List of printed materials and maps separated to Library (Box-folder 16 / 11)
  - Reports
    - Annual reports, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 16 / 12)
  - Miscellany
    - Agendas; "consensus" forms re local League's position on various issues; studies (re state and local government, traffic routes, etc.), 1975-1981 (Box-folder 16 / 13)
  - Clippings
    - re Flathead County League, 1954-1982 (Box-folder 16 / 14)
- League of Women Voters of Great Falls
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1987 (Box-folder 16 / 15)
  - Financial Records
    - Budgets; financial reports, 1955-1986 (Box-folder 16 / 16)
  - Minutes
    - General League meetings; Board meetings, 1955-1987 (Box-folder 17 / 1-3)
  - Organization
    - Membership and officer lists; bylaws, 1955-1986 (Box-folder 17 / 4)
  - Printed Materials
    - List of printed material separated to Library (Box-folder 17 / 5)
  - Reports
    - Annual reports (includes recommendations to National League), 1958-1981 (Box-folder 17 / 6-7)
  - Miscellany